welcome it's great to be here again for
another live Q&A I'd like to begin by
once again thanking all my subscribers
my viewers and all my patreon supporters
so as always we'll begin with the
questions from the patreon supporters
and so let's get to them this is always
so so interesting and enjoyable and I've
noticed that the the questions are
getting very very incisive and their
persecution so that's really really
impressive okay so the first question is
from patreon supporter McKenzie Levitt
and the question is what is the most
useful way to characterize relationship
between mind and brain so Thank You
McKenzie for your support so that's a
that's a very very hard question I you
could say and I think it would not be a
dismissive you could say that almost all
of my work as a cognitive sciences
scientist is directed towards trying to
answer that question if you'd asked me
that when I was in grad school was
shortly shortly thereafter I would have
given sort of a classic answer like
Jerry Fodor would give and say that the
mind is the software and the brain is
the hardware and like you can make the
distinction between like for example
word and then what's happening right
which is a way in which you're
organizing information processing as a
program that can be moved around to
different hardware and whereas the
hardware is the actual you know physical
stuff inside the machine and well I
think there's some important kernel of
truth in that I think the relationship
is now moved so I would now characterize
the relationship in a way that has moved
beyond that computational metaphor
whereas I think of minds relationships
the brain as the mind is a dynamical
system that is being run it can be
implemented on many different material
platforms but that dynamical system is
not just in the head in the brain it's
between the brain and the body
and between the brain body at the
embodied brain and the world and in a
form of dynamical coupling and so just
to give you a perhaps a different
analogy then instead of it like being
the software/hardware distinction you
can think of a dynamical system is
something like as I've sometimes use
like combustion combustion is a
self-organizing system but you know you
can run on different things and that's
why you can catch fire with wood and
then the what fire can spread to other
material and the combustion right it
isn't loft of particular material
implication it has to be connected to
you and implemented in something
material but it's not reducible to you
that material property so that's how I
would answer that the problem with
answering that question that way though
just to be as fair to the question as
possible is the word mind is very
equivocal you could be referring to
intelligence in which I think what we're
talking about and in the mind is a
dynamical system that's running
relevance realization on the embodied
embedded brain you could be talking
about consciousness which i think is a
higher-order thing etc so I'm answering
the questions for the very abstractly so
it would cover both intelligence and
consciousness and so that's why now
entering it's somewhat abstract Lee in
terms of its a dynamical system that is
running on the embodied and embedded
brain insofar as you are enacting
sensory motor behavior as you attempt to
solve problems and achieve your goals so
that's the that's the that's sort of my
overall abstract answer to that question
like I say I think that time is a better
way to answer that question which I
don't have time for right now is to go
away in ants and I try to give one
example of it answer one of them like
what's intelligence and then perhaps
what's consciousness and then more
difficult while what is that what is the
self
what's that what kind of relationship
that is does it air to the brain but at
least trying to give you an overall
response and so thank you very much for
that question answering that question is
kind of an answer today answering that
question not only for each one
intelligence consciousness to solve but
ant being able to answer that now for
each and all in an integrated manner I
think is the primary goal that defines
cognitive sciences discipline so I'm
saying that to indicate to you that I'm
giving you what I think is the best
proposal for how we will eventually be
able to answer that question I need you
to understand that it's of course
controversial and it's not something
that we have completed cognitive science
is not in any way it finished in a
position to claim to have finished
answering that question by any means
okay so let's move to the next question
so this is also from McKenzie and this
is what is your favorite example of a
film that symbolizes the meaning crisis
ah that's that's very good there's it
depends what by what you mean I like the
matrix insofar as it represents the
meaning crisis but also portrays
neoplatonism and narcissism as the
answer to the meeting crisis so the way
the meeting crisis is symbolized writers
of course he feels and then this is
where in the linear as a discussion with
Morpheus and he talks about how he you
know things just don't feel right it's
like a splinter in his mind and and
that's very much a way of trying to get
a phenomenology of the meaning crisis
that sense of that knowing sense of
being out of sorts and other place and
disconnected from oneself and reality
and then what's interesting is that
that's metaphor and that is understood
in through the metaphor the the gnostic
metaphor the Neoplatonic metaphor of the
cave the cave that has becoming the
entrapped the entrapping prison and so
that brings we're there also a sense of
entrapment which I sometimes wonder is
that perhaps sometimes the people who
are criticizing
physicalism from a religious perspective
if one of their motives is they feel
that physicalism is not adequately
representing their sense of entrapment
or that essential entrapment and if that
is the case I'm putting that out as a
potential hypothesis to explore in
discussion with people then I would like
to enter into a discussion with people
about that and then see if there's a way
of addressing it I think also the true
mention bill is one of my favorites as
well and obviously the pun is in his
name is meant to be taken seriously it
also has a sort of a gnostic theme he's
trapped in an inauthentic existence and
then there's the quest to try and get
connection to himself by to someone he
genuinely loves and to the world as it
really is and of course that again
represents some of the main things that
people are doing when they're trying to
respond to the meaning crisis I think
also and so calling it favorite might be
the wrong adjective but I think a movie
that I take very seriously and I've been
writing some wicky-wicky letters with
David Chapman about this and Andrew
Sweeney has been commenting on those as
well as in some really brilliant ways
these Joker and what what I one of the
things I'm trying to explore is how
Joker represents a shift from the zombie
mythos as a primary way of understanding
the meaning crisis which is the sort of
amorphous collective hoard to an
individual who represents malevolent
narcissism taken to its final sort of
form of degradation see narcissism
represents all that's left of relevance
realization is relevance to the self a
very you know the sort of primitive
initiating aspects of relevance
realization and the Joker
right of course disconnected radically
disconnected I'll try not to do any
spoilers here radically disconnected
from himself his world the people that
are supposed to be the individuals he
loves so he's clearly suffering from it
but what he does is he represents a
shift towards something and I think he
represents a shift that we're seeing in
our socio-political culture which is the
shift towards a malevolent kind of
absurdism because one of the things that
narcissism can do to defend its
last-ditch gasp of trying to maintain
connection is to cover the absurdity of
its set you know of itself narcissism is
inherently absurd position it can it
tries to cover that absurdity by making
as much of the world absurd around it
and in that way the suffering of the
disjunct between the absurdity of
narcissism and the intelligibility and
value and significance of reality is
undermined post truth and all that stuff
and thereby the right the the difference
between the absurd inner life of the
narcissist and the world in which they
are dwelling is completely flattened and
I think we see that happening in joke or
so the ship there the it maybe I don't
know if it's going to be a comprehensive
shift but the potential to have shifted
from the zombie mythos to the Joker
mythos as a way of articulating a new
way in which people are appropriating
and experiencing and interpreting the
meaning crisis I think is something that
we should all pay very careful attention
to particularly of course because of the
intimate connection between the Joker's
program and a random chaotic violence
so the next question is from the picture
on Mike most people see themselves in a
world in terms of being a subject in a
world of other objects is the split
between self and other hardwired into it
or is it something that can be overcome
with the right spiritual practice so
thank you very much Mike for your
support and for your actual question so
that's a difficult question it's a
question that I'm actually working on
right now I've done some work with an RA
Elizabeth long I'm also doing some other
current work on this this question of
the self its work I'm doing with a
democratic and Madeleine at the end on
the cognitive continuum from insight to
enlightenment so there's a sense in
which the subject object distinction
which is of course was valorized by
Aristotle into the sort of fundamental
logic of his metaphysics there's a sense
in which we can overcome that in that we
can move to forms of cognition that do
not depend on a subject predicate format
in order to be processed which is the
core of propositional processing but you
might say well even in sort of
procedural and perspectival
states like flow where you're feeling
that one there still may be a sort of a
fundamental orientation difference
between sort of here and there and of
course that itself can also disappear
when you get into a state called the
pure consciousness event in which there
is no distinction between inner and
outter between self and others so that
there are states we can get into that
progressively move us on a continuum
where the sense of the egoic
autobiographical self and inner and
outer those various phenomenological
aspects of self and other can definitely
be reduced and in some state
in some states they seem to disappear
I've experienced it myself
however I do not think that that then
means that the self in terms of its
functionality disappears so if we take
the machinery of the self to be
ultimately the processes by which this
organism manages manages the
combinatorial explosion of information
available to it and does framing I don't
think we can move to a state in which we
are frameless and we're not framing I
don't think that makes any sense and so
in that sense they are always in we're
always so I I'm suspicious of people who
claim that they completely have no self
and if the dot if what they mean by that
is there is no process by which
relevance realization is going on I
don't know what that is or Hawaii you
want it I don't know what it is to be Oh
what what what the state looks like it
may be even it could even be called a
mental state at all in which one is
completely overwhelmed by combinatorial
explosion and why that would in any way
be that one so I think there's always in
this sense the machinery of the self
that is the machinery of framing in a
self-organizing fashion I don't think
there's some soul behind that my cards
on the table and be honest with people I
don't think there's anything beyond the
self-organizing processes I don't think
there's anything to the self in its deep
fundamental machinery beyond the
self-organizing of the framing that's
happening and relevance realization and
in that sense I think there's always an
inner and an outer there's distinctions
going on for processing now
phenomenologically you may not be
experiencing in any inner and outer but
I'm pretty sure because I've studied the
pure consciousness event that you're
still because it still has salience in
it it still has a sense of here and
there so now there's a unity to it these
are all in fact venerated in the
tradition
that to me indicates the relevance
realization is still going on and
therefore there's there's still the
distinction between what's in the frame
and what is outside the frame which has
been indispensably excluded from
processing so that your cognition is not
overwhelmed by a combinatorial explosion
of information and options etc etc so we
should be careful and and I've made this
point before we should be very careful
in moving from our phenomenology to our
theoretical explanations of
functionality that we should not simply
import from phenomenology to
functionality the fact that there are
phenomenological states of consciousness
in which the autobiographical self
disappears and even the sense of inner
and outer experience disappears like
experience those myself doesn't leave me
to conclude for reasons that I've just
argued that the the sort of functioning
machinery of the self the self
organization of relevance realization
that gives you a cognition it's coherent
integrated and developmental abilities I
don't think that can be made to
disappear by any spiritual practice now
the question then of course remains
which ones are relevant to our self
viento and our moral development
I think overcoming you know biases of
egocentrism getting more flexible in our
perspective of framing all these kinds
of things can be improved in a
significant way and insofar as these
altered states facilitate an enhancement
of our cognitive functioning such that
we can address perennial problems of
self-deception and self-destructive
behavior I think that's I think that's
the that's the normative standard by
which we should evaluate these claims to
removing the subject object distinction
and I'm not sure if there is any other
independent normativity that we could
bring to bear to evaluate those
it claims so that's my best attempt to
answer that question that's a really
good question and I'm gonna be talking a
lot more in after Socrates about
different kinds of self-knowledge and
the the the very great difference before
you between for example knowing your
auto by yourself autobiographically and
then becoming metacognitively aware the
self-awareness of of your right of your
of your awareness that kind of direct
procedural perspective on metacognition
so we're going to talk a lot about that
in in after Socrates so hopefully that
will also give some more a conceptual
vocabulary and theoretical grammar to
wrestle with the perennial problem of
what should we think about the our
adherence to and the nature of the self
so I'd like to turn to another patreon
supporter Sergei by carrying that sorry
Mack Arkin thank you and just let me saw
that I'm sorry for mispronouncing your
name but take comfort in the fact that
nobody gets my name right guys so so
thank you again for your support I'm
gonna read your question in a recent Q&A
you talked about San Harris and
mentioned that his meditation practice
is to focus on transforming the mind but
not on transforming how the world
reveals itself to one's mind could you
elaborate more on ways on the ways how
medicate meditation can be adjusted to
focus more on the latter transforming
the world or on other practices that
could be employed for that purpose maybe
you could also point to some guidance on
how to do that practice guided
meditation course by you or someone else
so one thing and I've argued there
Senate published a paper with Leo
Ferraro on this a chapter in the book on
that's what's it called hypnosis and
meditation towards a contest but is it
towards the science of conscious flames
I think is what it's called and there's
an article in there on mindfulness and
we argued that the meditative practice
of stepping back and looking at the mind
and I made a similar argument
in the video skiers should be
complimented with contemplative
practices that are meant to look out
into how the world is disclosing itself
to you now of course you're transforming
the mind but the goal there is to
transform the mind in such a way that
you're transforming how the world is
disclosed to you so meta is a practice
like that and what you do in that
practice is you can do it either
imaginative layer you can do it
literally but let's say it imagine Italy
you would call up the image of somebody
in your life and then you direct a sort
of open-heartedness towards them not
that's not the goal although I think
some versions of loving-kindness or
contemplative practice misrepresent that
as it's a method it's meant to put you
into a state of openness and receptivity
and what you're trying to do is become
aware of the identity you're assuming
and the identity or signing that whole
Co identification process because that
of course is affecting how the world is
able to disclose itself to you if your
identity is locked and the right and and
then it's locked to write the identity
or assuming is locked and then it's
locked to the identity or signing that
things ability to disclose itself to you
in new ways is seriously truncated and
hampered your salient landscape it is
sort of really boxing it in almost like
an annoying dog problem so one of the
practices you can do is add meta
practice and you can you can buy books
on how to do that or loving-kindness
there is also in the book from the
Buddhist tradition there's what's called
contemplating the marks of existence in
which you enter you first get into a
meditative meditative state but then you
direct your attention outward and you
try to for example contemplate how
everything is interconnected or how
everything is impermanent you try to
realize that's not think it or believe
it but realize it as phenomenologically
present in your experiences so that the
world can we can figure how it discloses
itself to you I also find that for me
Alexia Divina the sacred reading is a
way in which I can used text sacred
texts to
be a medium and a vehicle through which
reality can disclose itself to me in
different ways so there's some excellent
books on Lexy Oh Davina out there
they're mostly from a Christian
tradition a tradition there are some
versions of it also form within a
Neoplatonic tradition I will at some
point do some instructional videos on
some more of the condom meditative
practices contemplative practices like
Co Davina
you also want to do a moving practice of
some kind they get you involved with
like like moving Tai Chi and get you
involved with other people
sparring in it because that also opens
that machinery up to having the world
disclosed in a more flexible manner and
and and again whether one of the things
I'm working on really seriously right
now with the help of a lot of great
people is trying to understand authentic
relating practices authentic discourse
and in this whole notion of trying to
get the meta Secretary Knology of
dialectic because dialectic was
precisely directed towards opening up
trying to get the process of an agave
going so that the world can open itself
up in conjunction with how the psyche
has opened up and that's happens in a
mutually accelerating fashion so those
that's a whole those that's a whole set
of practices that I think you could
consider for trying to create a state of
mind in a state of being because it's
not just a state of mind it's a state of
right such a state of consciousness or
cognition it's also a state of you know
how of identification of existential
mode that you can cultivate in order to
you afford the world disclosing it
itself to you and are more ongoing and
perhaps deeper fashion so here's another
question from McKenzie leave it does the
reality that is disclosed in
relationship habits owns ontological
status so that's a that's I think that's
a really that's that's
good question so I've tried to indicate
that I think so when I tried to coin the
term transgender Kate the the
ontological status of things like
affordances because of course if they're
the fact that the grunting you know the
glasses the mug is graspable it's not
just a property event not just a
property of me but a real relationship
between me and this person goes back to
Gibson it's sort of a central example
for this but there's other there's many
ways there's many other ways like
Fitness biological Fitness is a real
relation so I think it has an
ontological status and that's what I've
called the transitive and I've tried to
argue that the the the problem is the
words so I'm hesitating because we use
these words in a slippery fashion
subjective and objective are often used
as ontological terms but they're often
also epistemological terms they're about
ways of knowing as opposed to kinds of
being and we slide between them and so
insofar as the trend rejected is its own
ontological category I think it is more
primordial than subjectivity and
objectivity as epistemological
categories it's the ontological thing
that grounds the relationship between
subjective and objective ways of knowing
and so I do think it has its own
ontological status now I think that
ultimately maps into the fact that
something like structural realism is
correct in which I think what's
fundamentally most real and physics
seems to be moving this way and in fact
there's many there's many people in
theoretical physics are very interested
in the philosophical position of
structuralism because what structurally
also you can look at lady mins book
everything must go as an example of that
and and this is the idea that ultimately
what's most real are the real patterns
the real relations and that
we should take that as the ontological
primitive and then see objects and
events and and whatnot coming out of
that I think you could make a good case
and some people have that Whitehead was
arguing for something like that so
insofar as trans jacked if 'ti is a real
relationship that grounds subjectivity
objectivity in the way I've described I
think it is a species of the real
relations the real patterns that I think
are ultimately the fundamental building
blocks now that's that that of course is
a very controversial thing to say the
the west from Aristotle on has tended to
view objects the things that are related
as primary and then the relation as
derivative which is of course the direct
opposite of what you see in Eastern
philosophy in which the relations take
priority and they're the relati emerge
out of the of the relations and this
also has to do with the fact that the
West equates realness with actuality
whereas Eastern philosophy sees often
sees real possibility as more real than
actuality and so these are some very
important contrasts but you do see with
the rise of structural realism and the
procession of real patterns the very
real chance that the West might be
shifting to something much more
analogous to what has been prevalent in
the East in which real relations and
systems of relations are the ontological
ground from which everything else can be
seen to emerge so that's my best attempt
to answer the question on the
ontological status relationship so on
the next question is from Christina
Dragonetti who is a patreon supporter
thank you Christina
geography for the wakening course it
would be very helpful
no we haven't made a bibliography
I'm going to do I'm probably at the end
of the course I do put up the panels but
I understand having all the books listed
at one point would be very good so I do
hope to have that done like I say by the
by the uploading of episode 50 when
we've made a bibliography of all the
texts available I don't know there I
know that future thinkers they're doing
a believe it's every Monday they meet
and do a watch party and they're going
through episodes of the awakening in the
mini crisis series and they are they
they have a link to all the course notes
I think there's a running bibliography
there as well so you might want to check
that out that that is definitely
something that's going to happen there
like I said there are course notes
because of the watch parties that future
thinkers are doing excellent discussion
of my work by the way there by the
people that tune in for that I've been
very appreciative and grateful for that
there's also some really excellent
commentary and some of it critical but
yeah but constructive criticism by
Andrew Sweeney he's got he's got a site
on the medium where he's got a
commentary on all all the videos and I
think it's an excellent commentary i
think it makes material very accessible
without in any way dumbing or watering
it down so I recommend taking a look at
that excellent commentary and reflection
if you want to see some more critical
more critical take by Andrew on on my
work you did take a look not only at
some of the stuff he does in the
commentary I andrew is a great guy we
have a good relationship so but he and
Alexander Bardot who also I have a have
a good working relationship with they
did a recent video on criticizing me and
in comparison to the
Jordan Peterson I know that I responded
it and I think there's some excellent
discussion about that okay so let's take
a look at the next question from Steven
last well a patron thank you for your
support and Jordan Hall has taken to
calling me Johnny D I like it is it cool
that we started calling you Johnny v um
so I want this there's a lot more to
that and I yeah I I thought I talked to
Jordan directly about this so and I need
to relate this story and I don't mean to
be overly personal this is about how
people are going to call me so I suppose
it's appropriate to be a little bit more
personal right now not that long ago
let me turn around and or explain I used
to live and with being a very difficult
situation for me often socially I'm very
socially phobic and I often did not have
much in common with the people that
lived around me they were not bad people
and I'm not judging them as people if
and when I did that in the past I
apologize I think that was wrong with me
like wrong but nevertheless there was a
there was disconnect I didn't belong
there and I mean this is something that
has happened to me periodically through
my life a realization of not belonging
perhaps what I got interested in
relevance realization but so I used to
go to parties and social gatherings and
there was a there was a woman there and
like we weren't friends in the sense of
spending any time together outside of
these social circumstances but we we
were very friendly acquaintances and she
was quite high stud status woman she was
very driven you know attractive halo
effect very smart successful mother
raising great kids so she's very high
sort of high status and she went out of
her way to make me feel welcome when I
would come to those parties and
gatherings
and she would do that no one had ever
done this before by saying hey it's
Johnny ve or welcome Johnny V and that
meant a great deal to me and then a
great great deal to me unfortunately and
know that long ago she died quite young
and unexpected and very significant loss
and so when Jordan started doing that it
called up and you know it's a little bit
bittersweet but it called out the deep
appreciation I had for that wonderful
woman and it also made me feel because I
thought it was constant he was also
welcoming me into a social situation in
the same kind of manner and so I'm
deeply deeply appreciated appreciative
of that
so as long as people understand that
context I'm very happy for people to
refer to me that way I've talked to
Jordan about it and I'd like they said
I've expressed my gratitude to him for
saying that and I've said to him I've
asked him if you know if he likes saying
it and I said if he wants to continue
referring to me in that way I coming
from him especially I would really look
I would really like and appreciate that
but as long as people understand that
there's a there's I understand it's
playful then it's great and I appreciate
that as long as people understand that
for me all of that is there but there's
also a more serious depth to that
appellation and as long as they respect
that and and and the woman that is
called to mind by that appellation I'm
happy for people to refer to me as
Johnny V so thank you very much for
asking that question and once again
thank you to he's becoming a good friend
on somebody I do you believe respect
thank you to Jordan Hall
so a another question from a patreon
supporter so this is Ivor thank you
for your support your question is what
are the baby steps that lead from the
mentality of a wanton or a half or
Hamlet towards wisdom yeah so this this
this is I've ordered this this is the
this is the question that I think this
is the burning question right now
there's a Kairos around this um David
fuller was in from well rebel wisdom
last week two films four videos and he
and I were talking in Peter Lindbergh
but was there we're talking to about you
know this this turn towards you know
practice how do we take these ideas how
do we take this emerging intelligibility
and translate it effectively into
interaction I mean that's that's that's
the that is the central question part of
what when I'm like what I'm one of
directing the after Socrates video
series towards so I think I think a good
way in bellman who introduces the idea
of this problem with the wantin a good
way of getting into this that's a I
think a baby step is something that I
talk about in this series which is
learning how to get into the flow state
within movement within interaction the
reason for that is because there's all
the flow state isn't Universal it's a as
far as we can tell you know there's no
you know it's the same kind of
description and evaluation appreciation
of the state across you know genders
socio-economic groups occupational
positions language group all of it you
know we find people getting into this
and so why is that valuable for being
neither a wanton nor Hamlet because in
the flow state you get the you get the
immersion you get the the contact right
with the world that the wanted has
you've got you've got that immersion
into the the contact and the interaction
and the machinery of your agency
but you also have what Hamlet has you
have this you don't have you don't have
propositional metacognition but you have
this you have that you have this
procedural prospective tableau
metacognition that you because you you
have tremendous flexibility there's so
much creativity and flexibility and the
ability to innovate on the fly this is
why you see it in martial arts and jazz
so you get you get the flexibility of
Hamlet without getting right the way his
continual stepping back reflection and
narrative self discussion said monologue
the soliloquy as the epitome of that is
just you know innovating and improv
renting him from taking action so you
you get the ball that you get the
positive the family you get their
flexibility and the ability to redirect
and innovative and be you know very
intelligent I would even argue deeply
rational in your interactions and then
write but you get that you get you do
get the the coupling to the world and
the immersion and the machinery of your
agency what's so important about flow is
your agency is enhanced even well that
that sort of mattering narrative the ego
drops away the the continual how's my
biography and how's my hair thing in
your head which really puts to low lie
that egos claim in its narrativity as
I'm running the show and without me you
can't be an agent and that's just in the
end because flow universally
provides counter evidence to that lie
because what it shows is that can drop
away and your agency is precisely
enhanced then that can really also help
address you know a tendency towards
being a being a very egocentric and in
your perspective so all of these things
right the flow state helps you to take
those baby steps over beyond both the
wanton and Hamlet I would recommend
slingerland book trying not to try
because what you want to do is you want
to find places where you get a very good
taste for the flow State and then learn
how to restructure your experience and
broaden the places in
which you can get into the flow state
and that will help I think get those
baby steps towards some fundamental
aspects of the steps towards our wisdom
all right
so so we now have an announcement
thank you to my patreon supporters your
support is crucial to continuing to
produce these videos and for supporting
the science we're doing deploying
solutions in the meeting crisis and I
although I'm reading what amar has
written I'm totally behind it when I
think you and and I totally mean it so
thank you very much for life we're
shifting to live questions from the chat
please identify yourself as a patreon
subscriber to receive priority for your
question so the next question is from
patreon
Andrea Henry D and thank you for your
support Andrea and the question is what
do you think about animal ethics and
then treatment enrolled in human society
that's a very that's a very important
question so I thought a lot about this
and I've reflected on it in on my life
and it's affected my personal practice
so I'll try to understand sorry I'm
trying to answer the question about what
I think but I'm trying to also justify
it in terms of argumentation because of
course you know this is something that
around witches are wrong which is
controversy I try to understand one of
the sort of one of the primary projects
of an ethical way of life is to protect
and to protect produce promote meaning
making creatures for reasons that I've
argued here in Q&A and I've argued on
the series I think we are wired to find
I think we are wired to find meaning
making and meaning makers inherently
valuable and I think that is the
ultimate grounding the the you know the
Mitchell I know that with others the
Heidegger talks well I think
the ultimate grounding of ethics the
ethical is that which reliably helps to
produce protect and promote meaning
making and meaning makers so I think
that insofar as we have good evidence
for organisms being capable of such
meaning making we have a obligation to
them even though they might not be able
to reciprocate with justice to us
because justice is only capable where
there's a reciprocity between moral
agency so I don't think we can expect
justice for example from animals but
nevertheless we should extend ethical
obligation towards them
now that gets in that of course there's
always the question about where the
where's the morality groans in the
metaphysics and the ontology I'll tell
you how long I've thought about this and
I'm I don't think I can have I I think
my position is a plausible one but I do
know what I do not think it forecloses
and I'm not trying to foreclose on
bringing this into discussion or other
people's position I've taken to not
eating creatures for which we have good
reason to believe there is intelligence
because I think of intelligence as the
behavioral marker of relevance
realization and that relevance
realization is the ultimate grounding of
what we of the meaning making we're
talking when we're talking about
existential kinds of meaning so I don't
eat for example mammals so I don't eat
octopus it doesn't come off but I
wouldn't eat crow no pun intended by the
way no idiomatic
pun intended there but because of
Caledonian crows intelligence so I think
that's very clear I mean you know and
that comes up too they eat sushi often
octopus I think is more intelligent than
a Dalek it is pretty clear evidence
about that
you know and that's why I can't I can't
see myself I couldn't see myself eating
a dog or a cat I think most people would
agree with that and I think just then
saying well but I'm okay with eating a
pig that strikes me is just it's not
defensible the reasons forward but she
wouldn't need a dog or a cat seem to
also preclude you eating a pig now
whether or not we that should be
extended I do eat chicken I'm not
convinced that they have very much
intelligence I could be wrong about that
I'm open to that I do not want to get
flooded with emails from vegans it's
like please I
there's vegans in my family and I talk
to them on a regular basis I understand
a lot of these positions I do reflect on
them I have revised my position of my
eating habits I'm not as I said about
foreclosing what I'm trying to say is I
know that these these physicians have a
law of emotional a lot of them emotional
resonance and value to them and as they
should but what I'm trying to do is
answer the question is honestly and
thoroughly as I can so for me I have
tried to take what seems to me
well evidenced plausible accounts of
creatures that do not show it that do
clearly have the intelligence that gives
them the kind of meaning making that I
find inherently valuable and therefore I
extend our moral privileges to them now
this is on a continuum right if we if
human beings if their lives are at risk
and their only way they could survive or
to kill mammals like perhaps you know
certain indigenous communities then of
course and that's the only way in which
they can survive and not starve then I
think that becomes a legitimate thing so
I think it's in poor
that we figure out how to talk about
this and in a very coherent manner and
this is a place in which I don't want to
sound too imperialistic but there's a
place in which cognitive science could
really help make a difference I think
until we get very clear on consciousness
and cognition and intelligence and
meaning-making we we should stop making
absolute claims about how we should make
Earth undertake our ethical practices I
think we should do what I've tried to do
here I think we should make possible we
should make plausibility arguments and
then try to be consistent around them we
have to address this issue we can't put
it off because not only animals the
emergent artificial general intelligence
is eventually going to get to the status
what we're going to have to raise this
question as well for those machines in
England right and so let's why not do it
now so we've got really good practice at
it for when the inevitable machines
arrive we'll have a better repertoire of
skills for addressing it and knowledge
for addressing it and along the way
maybe we'll treat our fellow organisms
more appropriately all right so here's a
question from page one Rob thank you for
your support if you were to change one
or two things about the nature of public
education or college education or for
better growth and future fitness again
people to society what would you do and
why it could be as radically different
from today's system of education as you
like thank you for that permission from
God so if I could change I think I we
need to do we need to bring back what
we've lost we we had a knowledge
institution and a wisdom institution and
they were coupled together and there was
cross-pollination cross fertilization
between them and then the plastic
Reformation and a bunch of other things
shut down the monasteries and then the
university attached to the state as
opposed to the monastery and I think
that has been very problematic
because we have lost places for which
people in which people can cultivate
wisdom self-transcendence pursued the
understanding of the knowledge that
they've acquired figure out how that
translates into existential modes
interactional relationships all of that
has been lost so if I could do one thing
and this is radical we need to bring
something back like what the monastery
was now of course because of the plural
of plural society we're in and I'm not
trying to in any way undermine that I
think we need to do something like a
secular monasteries or maybe like a
forest it is do it where you have the
monastic Academy where it's not tied to
a particular religious tradition or
religious institution and that gives
people nevertheless something that they
could do in conjunction with the
acquisition of knowledge that they're
doing at the university and we might
want to do you know something even a
preparatory of that I thought at the
high school level if we could other
society it's like when I say that I know
lots of people are out there rolling
their eyes right it's like other
cultures have and still do and all our
culture did for a very long time so
there's nothing sort of natural or the
waves has to be about the way we do it
now and so it would it would be good if
we thought about how wisdom could be
brought into education I know Robert
Sternberg has done a lot of work on this
about how to bring wisdom into the
educational situation and he also has I
think a recent book on how to apply
wisdom to the world's problems to try
and show the value that such an
education could bring like to people as
being citizens good citizens of the
world not just sort of efficacious
agents within their own life so that
that was a that would be something
change I would like to see
so now I want to move to a question from
a patron Carter thank you for your
support Carter what do you make of the
apparent find over Western civilization
in the art world of shifting from the
genre of tragedy to that of horror aside
from the increased visceral potential of
modern artistic mediums
how would you exploit the cultural and
psychological shifts in emphasis here
especially as it relates to alienation
agency in the mean crisis so I already
alluded to some of this when the the
discussion I had about shudder and
because the Joker of course sits right
on horror I don't think this is any
spoilers because it's abstract enough
but no there's there's the opposite of
dramatic irony when you're watching
Joker like him you don't know in the
movie what's real and that's constantly
when you things start to get stabilized
the movie shuffles them and you think
you've got sort of oh that's the correct
political labeling for that or this is
really happening and then the movie
shuffles it around and it puts you in
this constantly right tenuous grasp of
yourself of the main character which of
course with whom you of course it's a
movie you're identifying to some degree
and then the world of them if so there's
this horrific element in it not and I
don't mean just the violence I mean that
sense of what's real here and that this
is so unstable yet it's compelling and
the drawn-in it's it's very muddy it has
some of that numinous aspect of horror
to it and I think why horror is becoming
more prevalent is precisely because it
indicates as I've said it indicates that
the the loss of a sense of contact and
connection has gone from being a dull
ache to being a throbbing pain and I
think what you see in Joker for example
is pain that is not ameliorated but
eventually identified with as
the only last possible motivation which
is I'm going to burn the world because
then my pain and the world once again
are connected and so that I think is a
very worrying trend that we're seeing I
think the horror is also an attempt to
intensify that sense of absurdity and
alienation
because our culture in general tries to
retrieve significance being significant
with carving intensity our culture is
beset by there's no depth to this so
what I'll do is make it as intense as
possible so they can overstimulate you
and overwhelm you that is the last
gasping shadow right of God it's right
it's but you used to be something which
filled you with awe and overwhelmed you
there's there's nothing of that so what
we can do though is we can just make it
so intense so literal so stimulating
that that intensity at least momentarily
gives you a surrogate for the depths of
significance but notice notice the that
you know the hallmark you find in people
like Jesus and Buddha where they talk
about the peace that passes all
understanding Jesus is where Buddha the
Buddha says very similar thing as the
hallmark of the genuine experience of
significance and depth there is no such
piece of understanding the peace that
passes understanding in these horror
genres and the fact that we could no
longer find peace and that we can no
longer find significance and all we can
pursue is the intensity that math masks
the lack of peace and pretends so
pretentious to be the depth of
significance I think points to the fact
that the meaning crisis is accelerating
not just in its pervasiveness but in its
profundity in terms of the pain its
inflicting on people so this is the last
question so this is from patrons for
private subscriber mohali a board Olli
thank you for your support do you think
peer coaching or peer mentorship could
be part of the ecology practices needed
to address the meeting crisis buta their
scalability yes very much this this came
up explicitly as some of you know I've
been engaging in circling practices with
other people particularly in Parkman
sort of ethnographic a partnership with
Peter Lindbergh and Peter pointed out
something that he found that I had said
and one of the circling practices as
we're very sort of helpful I mentioned
that in circling what you're creating is
peers and then I was like I said you do
sort of want to play on the word peer
because it also mean peer also needs to
look deeply into it and I think creating
peerage is a way to get distributed
cognition to generate a flow state that
exams are the collective intelligence we
need in order for addressing the project
as Jordan Hall said of trying to create
in both the top-down and bottom-up
fashion and Shepherd and husbandry of an
ecology of practices for addressing and
ameliorating the meeting crisis so I I
think yes and and their scalability is
very important precisely because I take
our poly and it pays criticism that any
attempt to I don't I don't see myself is
trying to replace but I'll just use that
term for now you need to attempt to try
and replace religion with sort of a
secular alternative faces the fact that
the religions have figured out
how to be scalable in a very profound
way and so finding I think scalability
is an important normative standard that
we should hold any purported ecology of
practices to if we wanted to be able to
address another meeting crisis so I want
to thank you all for joining me on and
this Q&A as always it was very enjoyable
the questions are always so interesting
and there's so many more I wanted to get
to you but as always time is the thief
that steals away our life we're doing
these every third Friday of the month
just so you guys any of you guys have
just come to this for the first time you
can plan if you if you want to be
involved again and thank you again for
the subscribers over patron as you know
I'm not taking income from this it goes
into the very key foundation and it goes
back into something to finance the the
next series and worth it's being done in
the lab and the consciousness and wisdom
study allowed and you can of course if
you want to start and it would be
greatly appreciated to support my work
on the Munich crisis you can go to
patreon.com/scishow or baekje and join
if you want to support the work I'm
doing so I want one more time to thank
all of you and again thank Tamar and
Carina my tech team for their wonderful
support I couldn't do it without them
and I look forward to seeing you again
for our next Q&A thank you very much